As a clergyman,
كأحد رجال الدين
you can imagine how
يمكنكم أن تتخيلوا كيف
out of place I feel.
أشعر أني لا أنتمي إلى هذا المكان
I feel like a fish out of water,
أشعر مثل سمكة خرجت من الماء
or maybe an owl out of the air.
أو ربما بومة خرجت من الهواء
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I was preaching in San Jose some time ago,
كنت واعظا في سان خوسيه في وقت مضى
and my friend Mark Kvamme,
وقد قام صديقي مارك كامى
who helped introduce me
الذي ساعد في تقديمي
to this conference,
إلى هذا المؤتمر
brought several CEOs
بجلب العديد من كبار المديرين التنفيذيين
and leaders
وقادة
of some of the companies here in the Silicon Valley
بعض من الشركات هنا في وادي السليكون
to have breakfast with me, or I with them.
لكي يفطروا معي ، أو أفطر أنا معهم.
And I was so stimulated.
وكان ذلك حافزا لي
And had such -- it was an
وكانت أيضا
eye-opening experience
تجربة جديدة
to hear them talk about
للاستماع لهم وهم يتحدثون عن
the world that is yet to come
العالم الذي لم يأت بعد
through technology
من خلال التكنولوجيا
and science.
والعلوم
I know that we're near the end of this conference,
أعرف اننا قرب نهاية هذا المؤتمر
and some of you may be wondering
ولعل بعضكم يتساءل
why they have a speaker
لماذا لديهم الآن متحدث
from the field of religion.
من مجال الدين
Richard can answer that,
ريتشارد يمكنه الإجابة عن ذلك
because he made that decision.
لأنه من اتخذ هذا القرار
But some years ago I was on an elevator in Philadelphia,
ولكن منذ بضع سنوات كنت في مصعد في فيلادلفيا
coming down.
أنزل الى أسفل
I was to address a conference
لإلقاء كلمة في أحد المؤتمرات
at a hotel.
في فندق
And on that elevator a man said,
وعلى متن هذا المصعد سمعت أحدهم يقول
"I hear Billy Graham is staying in this hotel."
سمعت أن بيللي جراهام يمكث في هذا الفندق
And another man looked in my direction and said,
ونظر أحدهم إلي قائلا
"Yes, there he is. He's on this elevator with us."
نعم، وهو أيضا معنا في هذا المصعد
And this man looked me up and down
ونظر لي هذا الرجل من أعلى لأسفل
for about 10 seconds,
لمدة 10 ثوان
and he said, "My, what an anticlimax!"
ثم قال يا للسخافة !
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I hope
إني.. آمل
that you won't feel that these few moments with me
انكم لن تشعروا بأن هذه اللحظات معي.. سخيفة
after all these tremendous
بعد كل هذه المحادثات الهائلة
talks that you've heard,
التي استمعتم إليها للتو
and addresses, which I intend to listen to every one of them.
والخطب التي أنوي الاستماع إليها
But I was
لكني كنت
on an airplane in the east some years ago,
على طائرة في الشرق منذ عدة سنوات
and the man sitting across the aisle from me
وكان هناك رجل يجلس عبر الممر المقابل لي
was the mayor of Charlotte, North Carolina.
وكان هذا الرجل هو رئيس بلدية مدينة شارلوت في كارولينا الشمالية
His name was John Belk. Some of you will probably know him.
اسمه جون بيلك.. من المحتمل أن بعضكم يعرفه
And there was a drunk man on there,
وكان هناك رجل آخر في حالة سكر
and he got up out of his seat two or three times,
نهض من مقعده مرتين أو ثلاث مرات
and he was making everybody upset
وكان الجميع مستاءين مما كان يحاول القيام به
by what he was trying to do.
مما كان يحاول القيام به
And he was slapping the stewardess
كمحاولته التعرض للمضيفة
and pinching her as she went by,
والتحرش بها كلما مرت بجواره
and everybody was upset with him.
وكان الجميع مشمئزين
And finally, John Belk said,
وأخيرا ، قال له جون بيلك ،
"Do you know who's sitting here?"
هل تعرف من يجلس معنا الآن؟
And the man said, "No, who?"
وقال الرجل : لا ، من؟
He said, "It's Billy Graham,
فرد عليه جون إنه بيلي غراهام
the preacher."
الواعظ
He said, "You don't say!"
وقال : يالها من مفاجأة!
And he turned to me, and he said, "Put her there!"
ثم التفت إلي قائلا: ضعها هناك!
He said, "Your sermons have certainly helped me."
لقد ساعدتني خطبك بالتأكيد!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I suppose that that's true
وأعتقد أن هذا صحيح
with thousands of people.
مع الآلاف من الاشخاص
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I know that as you have been peering into the future,
وأنا أعلم أنه كما أنكم تتطلعون إلى المستقبل
and as we've heard some of it here tonight,
وكما سمعنا من البعض هذا المساء
I would like to live in that age
فأنا أود أن أعيش هذا العصر
and see what is going to be.
وأرى ما سيكون
But I won't,
لكن ذلك لن يحدث
because I'm 80 years old. This is my eightieth year,
لأنني أبلغ من العمر ثمانين عاما، وها هو عامي الثمانين
and I know that my time is brief.
ولم يبق أمامي الكثير..
I have phlebitis at the moment, in both legs,
أعاني الآن من التهاب الوريد في كلتا ساقي
and that's the reason that I had to have a little help in getting up here,
وهذا هو سبب احتياجي لبعض المساعدة كي أقف
because I have Parkinson's disease
لأني أعاني من مرض باركنسون أيضا
in addition to that,
بالإضافة الى ذلك،
and some other problems that I won't talk about.
بعض المشاكل الأخرى التي لن أتحدث عنها
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But this is not the first time
ولكن.. هذه ليست المرة الأولى
that we've had a technological revolution.
التي كانت لدينا ثورة تكنولوجية
We've had others.
هناك ثورات أخرى سابقة
And there's one that I want to talk about.
أريد التحدث عن إحداها
In one generation,
في غضون جيل واحد
the nation of the people of Israel
حدث لأمة شعب اسرائيل
had a tremendous and dramatic change
تغيير هائل وجذري
that made them a great power in the Near East.
جعل منها قوة عظمى في الشرق الأدنى
A man by the name of David
رجل يدعى داوود
came to the throne,
جاء الى العرش
and King David became one of the great leaders
وأصبح الملك داوود واحدا من القادة العظام
of his generation.
في جيله
He was a man of tremendous leadership.
لقد كان قائدا هائلا
He had the favor of God with him.
وكان الله معه
He was a brilliant poet,
وكان أيضا شاعرا لامعا
philosopher, writer, soldier --
فيلسوفا، كاتبا، وجنديا
with strategies in battle and conflict
لديه من الاستراتيجيات في المعارك
that people study even today.
ما يدرسه الناس ليومنا هذا
But about two centuries before David,
ولكن قبل قرنين من داوود
the Hittites
كان الحيثيون
had discovered the secret
قد اكتشفوا سر
of smelting and processing of iron,
صهر ومعالجة الحديد
and, slowly, that skill spread.
وشيئا فشيئا، انتشرت تلك المهارة
But they wouldn't allow the Israelis
ولكنهم لم يكونوا ليسمحوا للإسرائيليين
to look into it, or to have any.
بالتعرف على تلك المهارة
But David changed all of that,
ولكن داوود غير كل ذلك
and he introduced the Iron Age
وقدم عصر الحديد
to Israel.
لإسرائيل
And the Bible says that David laid up great stores of iron,
ويخبرنا الكتاب المقدس بقيام داوود بإنشاء مخازن الحديد
and which archaeologists have found,
والتي عثر عليها اليوم علماء الآثار
that in present-day Palestine,
في فلسطين
there are evidences of that generation.
مما يدل على وجود هذا الجيل
Now, instead of crude tools
والآن، بدلا من الأدوات الخام
made of sticks and stones,
المصنوعة من العصى والحجارة
Israel now had iron plows,
تمتلك إسرائيل الآن المحاريث
and sickles, and hoes
والمناجل والجرافات
and military weapons.
والأسلحة العسكرية
And in the course of one generation,
وخلال جيل واحد
Israel was completely changed.
تغيرت إسرائيل تماما
The introduction of iron, in some ways,
إدخال الحديد في بعض النواحي
had an impact
كان له أثر
a little bit like the microchip
كأثر الشرائح الإلكترونية الدقيقة على جيلنا
And
و..
David found
وجد داوود
that there were many problems that technology could not solve.
أن هناك العديد من المشاكل التي فشلت التكنولوجيا في حلها
There were many problems still left.
هناك العديد من المشاكل المهملة
And they're still with us, and you haven't solved them,
والتي لا تزل قائمة، وليس لديكم حل لها
and I haven't heard anybody here speak to that.
وأنا لم أسمع أحدا يتحدث هنا عن ذلك
How do we solve these three problems
كيف يمكننا حل هذه المشاكل الثلاث
that I'd like to mention?
التي أود ذكرها
The first one that David saw
أولها ما رآه داوود
was human evil.
هي شرور الإنسان
Where does it come from?
من أين تأتي؟
How do we solve it?
كيف يمكننا حل هذه المشكلة؟
Over again and again
أكثر من مرة بعد أخرى
in the Psalms,
و في المزامير ،
which Gladstone said was the greatest book in the world,
والتي وصفها جلادستون أنها أعظم كتاب في العالم
David describes the evils of the human race.
يصف داوود شرور الجنس البشري
And yet he says,
ويقول
"He restores my soul."
إنك (الله) تعيد لي روحي
Have you ever thought about what a contradiction we are?
هل سبق لك أن فكرت في أي تناقض ما نحن؟
On one hand, we can probe the deepest secrets of the universe
من جهة نستطيع بحث أعمق أسرار الكون
and dramatically push back the frontiers of technology,
وندفع بشكل كبير حدود التكنولوجيا
as this conference vividly demonstrates.
كما يوضح لنا هذا المؤتمر
We've seen under the sea,
رأينا ما في أعماق البحر
three miles down,
ثلاثة أميال لأسفل
or galaxies hundreds of billions of years
كما رأينا مجرات تبعد عنا بلايين السنوات
out in the future.
في المستقبل
But on the other hand,
لكن من جهة اخرى
something is wrong.
هناك خطأ ما
Our battleships,
بوارجنا
our soldiers,
جنودنا
are on a frontier now,
هي الآن على أحد الحدود
almost ready to go to war
شبه مستعدة لخوض الحرب.. مع العراق
Now, what causes this?
الآن ، ما هي أسباب ذلك؟!
Why do we have these wars in every generation,
لماذا لدينا هذه الحروب في كل جيل
and in every part of the world?
وفي كل بقعة من بقاع العالم؟!
And revolutions?
والثورات؟!
We can't get along with other people,
لا يمكننا أن نتعايش مع أشخاص آخرين
even in our own families.
حتى في أسرنا
We find ourselves in the paralyzing grip
نجد أنفسنا في حلقة محكمة
of self-destructive habits we can't break.
من التدمير الذاتي والعادات لا نستطيع التخلص منها
Racism and injustice and violence sweep our world,
والعنصرية.. والظلم والعنف تجتاح عالمنا
bringing a tragic harvest of heartache and death.
جالبة حصادا مأساويا من الحزن والموت
Even the most sophisticated among us
حتى الأكثر تطورا بيننا
seem powerless to break this cycle.
يبدو عاجزا عن كسر هذه الحلقة
I would like to see Oracle
أريد أن أرى أوراكل
take up that,
تتناول هذه المشكلة
or
أو
some other
أجد
technological geniuses work on this.
عباقرة التكنولوجيا تعمل على ذلك
How do we change man,
كيف يمكننا تغيير الإنسان
so that he doesn't lie and cheat,
حتى لا يقع في الكذب والخداع
and our newspapers are not filled with stories
وحتى لاتمتلئ صحافتنا بالقصص
of fraud in business or labor
عن الاحتيال في الأعمال والعمالة
or athletics or wherever?
أو الرياضة، أو أي مجال كان
The Bible says the problem is within us,
يقول الكتاب المقدس أن المشكلة تكمن فينا
within our hearts and our souls.
داخل قلوبنا وأرواحنا
Our problem is that we are separated
مشكلتنا هي انفصالنا
from our Creator,
عن خالقنا
which we call God,
الله
and we need to have our souls restored,
ونحن بحاجة إلى استعادة نفوسنا
something only God can do.
وهو ما لا يقدر على فعله إلا الله
Jesus said, "For out of the heart
قال يسوع : من القلب
come evil thoughts:
تأتي الأفكار الشريرة
murders, sexual immorality,
من عمليات القتل والفجور الجنسي
theft, false testimonies,
والسرقة ، وشهادات الزور
slander."
وقذف الأعراض
The British philosopher Bertrand Russell
الفيلسوف البريطاني برتراند راسل
was not a religious man,
لم يكن رجل دين
but he said, "It's in our hearts that the evil lies,
لكنه قال في قلوبنا يكمن الشر
and it's from our hearts
ومن قلوبنا.. يجب أن يستأصل
Albert Einstein --
ألبرت أينشتاين
I was just talking to someone, when I was speaking at Princeton,
كنت أتحدث لشخص ما -- عندما كنت في جامعة برينستون ،
and I met
عندما التقيت بالسيد اينشتاين
He didn't have a doctor's degree, because he said
لم تكن لديه درجة دكتوراه، وقد علل ذلك
nobody was qualified to give him one.
بأنه لايوجد من هو مؤهل لمنحه واحدة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But he made this statement.
إلا أنه قال
He said, "It's easier to denature plutonium
من الأسهل أن تفسد البلوتونيوم
than to denature the evil spirit of man."
من أن تفصل روح شريرة من رجل
And many of you, I'm sure,
والعديد منكم ، وأنا واثق
have thought about that
فكر في ذلك
and puzzled over it.
وتمعن النظر فيه
You've seen people
لقد رأيتم الناس
take beneficial technological advances,
يستفيدون من التقدم التكنولوجي
such as the Internet we've heard about tonight,
مثل الإنترنت كما سمعنا هذه الليلة
and twist them into something corrupting.
ثم يحولونها إلى شيء.. فاسد
You've seen brilliant people devise computer viruses
لقد رأيتم العقول اللامعة تبتكر فيروسات الكمبيوتر
that bring down whole systems.
والتي تسبب في فشل أنظمة بأكملها
The Oklahoma City bombing was simple technology,
تفجير مدينة اوكلاهوما تم باستخدام تكنولوجيا بسيطة
horribly used.
استخدمت بفظاعة
The problem is not technology.
فالمشكلة ليست في التكنولوجيا!
The problem is the person or persons using it.
المشكلة تكمن في الشخص أو الأشخاص الذين يستخدمونها!
King David said
قال الملك داوود
that he knew the depths of his own soul.
انه يعرف أعماق روحه
He couldn't free himself from personal problems
قال إنه لا يستطيع أن يحرر نفسه من المشاكل الشخصية
and personal evils
والشرور الشخصية
that included murder and adultery.
والتي شملت القتل والزنا
Yet King David sought God's forgiveness,
ومع ذلك سعى الملك داوود إلى مغفرة الله
and said, "You can restore my soul."
وقال : يمكنك استعادة روحي!
You see, the Bible teaches
رأيتم، والكتاب المقدس يعلمنا
that we're more than a body and a mind.
أننا اكثر من جسد وعقل
We are a soul.
نحن أنفس
And there's something inside of us
وأن هناك شيء ما بداخلنا
that is beyond our understanding.
خارج عن نطاق فهمنا
That's the part of us that yearns
إنه الجزء الذي يتوق
for God, or something more
لمعرفة الله، أو لشيء أبعد
than we find in technology.
مما نجد في التكنولوجيا
Your soul is that part of you that
روحك هي ذلك الجزء منك
yearns for meaning in life,
الذي يتوق لأن يكون له معنى في هذه الحياة
and which seeks for something beyond this life.
والذي يسعى لشيء وراء هذه الحياة.
It's the part of you that yearns, really, for God.
إنه ذلك الجزء منك الذي يتوق حقا لمعرفة الله
I find [that] young people all over the world
أجد الشباب في جميع أنحاء العالم
are searching for something.
يبحث عن شيء ما.
They don't know what it is. I speak at many universities,
انهم لا يعرفون ما هو.. لقد تحدثت في كثير من الجامعات ،
and I have many questions and answer periods, and
وكان هناك دائما وقت لاستقبال الأسئلة والرد عليها
whether it's Cambridge, or Harvard,
سواء كانت كامبريدج أو هارفارد
or Oxford --
أو أوكسفورد
I've spoken at all of those universities.
تحدثت في كل من هذه الجامعات
I'm going to Harvard in about three or four --
سأشارك في هارفارد في خلال ثلاثة أو أربعة
no, it's about two months from now --
لا ، بل في خلال شهرين تقريبا من الآن
to give a lecture.
لإلقاء محاضرة
And I'll be asked the same questions that I was asked
وسوف أسأل نفس الأسئلة التي سئلتها
the last few times I've been there.
في المرات القليلة التي كنت بها هناك
And it'll be on
وسوف تكون منها
these questions:
هذه الأسئلة
where did I come from? Why am I here? Where am I going?
من أين جئت؟ لماذا أنا هنا؟ أين أنا ذاهب؟
What's life all about? Why am I here?
ما هي الحياة؟ لماذا أنا هنا؟
Even if you have no religious belief,
حتى لو كنت بلا معتقد ديني
there are times when you wonder that there's something else.
هناك أوقات كنت تتساءل فيها أن هناك شيئا آخر
Thomas Edison also said,
وقد قال أيضا توماس أديسون
"When you see everything that happens in the world of science,
عندما ترى كل ما يحدث في عالم العلم
and in the working of the universe,
وفي أعمال الكون
you cannot deny that there's a captain on the bridge."
وقتها لا يمكنك أن تنكر، أن هناك قائد لكل هذا على الجسر
I remember once,
وأذكر مرة
I sat beside Mrs. Gorbachev
أني جلست إلى جانب السيدة غورباتشوف
at a White House dinner.
في عشاء في البيت الابيض
I went to Ambassador Dobrynin, whom I knew very well.
ذهبت إلى السفير دوبرينين الذي أعرفه جيدا
And I'd been to Russia several times under the Communists,
وكنت قد زرت روسيا عدة مرات، في ظل الشيوعيين
and they'd given me marvelous freedom that I didn't expect.
الذين أعطوني من الحرية ما لم أكن أتوقع
And I knew Mr. Dobrynin very well,
وكنت أعرف السيد دوبرينين جيدا
and I said,
وقلت له
"I'm going to sit beside Mrs. Gorbachev tonight.
سأجلس بجوار السيدة غورباتشوف الليلة
What shall I talk to her about?"
فيما يجب أن أتحدث إليها الليلة؟
And he surprised me with the answer.
وفاجأني الجواب
He said, "Talk to her about religion and philosophy.
قال: تحدث معها عن الدين والفلسفة
That's what she's really interested in."
هذا ما تهتم به فعلا
I was a little bit surprised, but that evening
لقد فوجئت بعض الشيء ، ولكن في ذلك المساء
that's what we talked about,
هذا ما تحدثنا عنه
and it was a stimulating conversation.
وقد كانت محادثة شيقة
And afterward, she said,
قالت بعدها
"You know, I'm an atheist,
أنت تعرف ، أنا ملحدة
but I know that there's something up there
ولكني أعلم أن هناك شيء ما
higher than we are."
أعلى مما نحن عليه
The second problem
المشكلة الثانية
that King David realized he could not solve
والتي أدرك الملك داوود أنه لم يستطع حلها
was the problem of human suffering.
هي المعاناة الإنسانية
Writing the oldest book in the world was Job,
وخلال كتابته لأقدم كتاب في التاريخ
and he said,
قال
"Man is born unto trouble as the sparks fly upward."
يولد الإنسان في شقاء
Yes, to be sure, science has done much to push back
نعم ، بالتأكيد ، والعلم لم يفعل الكثير لدحر
certain types of human suffering.
أنواع معينة من المعاناة الإنسانية
But I'm --
لكني
in a few months, I'll be 80 years of age.
في الأشهر القليلة القادمة سوف أكون في الثمانين من العمر
I admit that I'm very grateful
أعترف أني في غاية الامتنان
for all the medical advances
لكل التقدم الطبي
that have kept me in relatively good health
الذي جعلني في صحة جيدة نسبيا
all these years.
كل هذه السنوات
My doctors at the Mayo Clinic urged me
حثني أطبائي في مشفى مايو
not to take this trip out here to this -- to be here.
ألا أقوم بهذه الرحلة-- لأحضر إلى هنا
I haven't given a talk in nearly four months.
لم أقم بإلقاء خطاب منذ ما يقرب من أربعة أشهر
And when you speak as much as I do,
وعندما كنت أتكلم بقدر ما أفعل
three or four times a day,
ثلاث أو أربع مرات في اليوم
you get rusty.
فإنك تصدأ
That's the reason I'm using this podium
ولهذا السبب أستخدم هذا المنبر
and using these notes.
وهذه الملاحظات
Every time you ever hear me on the television or somewhere,
في كل مرة كنتم تسمعونني على التلفزيون ، أو أي مكان
I'm ad-libbing.
كنت أرتجل
I'm not reading. I never read an address.
لم أكن لأقرأ خطبة
I never read a speech or a talk or a lecture.
لم أكن لأقرأ حديثا، أو محاضرة
I talk ad lib.
فقط أرتجل
But tonight, I've
ولكن هذه الليلة كنت
got some notes here so that if
قد أحضرت بعض الملاحظات
I begin to forget,
حتى إذا ما نسيت
which I do sometimes,
وهذا ما أفعله أحيانا
I've got something I can turn to.
يمكنني أن أرجع إليها لتذكرني.
But even here among us,
ولكن حتى هنا بيننا
most --
ربما
in the most advanced society in the world,
في أكثر المجتمعات تقدما في العالم
we have poverty.
لدينا الفقر
We have families that self-destruct,
لدينا الأسر التي تدمر نفسها ذاتيا
friends that betray us.
والأصدقاء الذين يقومون بخيانتنا
Unbearable psychological pressures bear down on us.
وضغوط نفسية لاتحتمل تثقل كواهلنا
I've never met a person in the world
لم ألتق أبدا بأي شخص في العالم
that didn't have a problem
ليس لديه مشكلة
or a worry.
أو قلق
Why do we suffer? It's an age-old question
لماذا نعاني؟.. إنه سؤال قديم
that we haven't answered.
وليست لدينا إجابة
Yet David again and again said
ولم يزل داوود يقول مرارا وتكرارا
that he would turn to God.
أنه كان ليتوجه إلى الله
He said, "The Lord is my shepherd."
ويقول، إن الله هو الراعي
The final problem that David knew he could not solve
المشكلة الأخيرة التي علم داوود أنه لم يقدر على حلها
was death.
هي الموت
Many commentators have said that death
كثير من المعلقين قالوا إن الموت
is the forbidden subject of our generation.
هو موضوع محرم على جيلنا
Most people live as if
يعيش معظم الناس وكأنهم
they're never going to die.
لن يموتوا
Technology projects the myth
تصور التكنولوجيا لنا أسطورة
of control over our mortality.
السيطرة على وفياتنا
We see people on our screens.
نرى على شاشاتنا
Marilyn Monroe is just as beautiful on the screen
مارلين مونرو كما هي، جميلة
as she was in person,
كما لو كانت هي حقيقة
and our -- many young people think she's still alive.
وكثير من شبابنا يعتقد أنها على قيد الحياة
They don't know that she's dead.
إنهم لا يعرفون أنها ماتت
Or Clark Gable, or whoever it is.
أو كلارك جابل أو أي كان
The old stars, they come to life.
نرى النجوم القديمة تبعث إلى الحياة
And they're --
وأنهم
they're just as great on that screen as they were in person.
وأنهم أحياء على الشاشة كما لو كانوا حقيقة
But death is inevitable.
ولكن لا مفر من الموت
I spoke some time ago to
لقد تحدثت قبل فترة من الزمن
a joint session of Congress, last year.
في جلسة مشتركة للكونغرس ، في العام الماضي
And we were meeting in that room,
وكنا مجتمعين في تلك الغرفة
the statue room.
غرفة التماثيل
About 300 of them were there.
نحو الثلاثمئة كانوا هناك
And I said, "There's one thing that we have in common in this room,
وقلت : هناك شيء واحد مشترك بيننا في هذه القاعة
all of us together, whether Republican or Democrat,
علينا جميعا -- سواء كننا جمهوريين أو ديمقراطيين
or whoever."
أو أي كنا
I said, "We're all going to die.
قلت : كلنا سنموت
And we have that in common with all these great men of the past
وهذا مشترك بيننا وبين كل رجال الماضي العظام
that are staring down at us."
الذي ينظرون إلينا الآن
And it's often difficult for young people
وهذا غالبا ما يكون من الصعب على الشباب
to understand that.
أن يستوعبوه
It's difficult for them to understand that they're going to die.
من الصعب عليهم أن يفهموا أنهم سيموتون
As the ancient writer of Ecclesiastes wrote,
وكما كتب كاتب سفر الجامعة
he said, there's every activity under heaven.
قال: هناك وقت لكل شيء تحت السماء
There's a time to be born,
هناك وقت للميلاد
and there's a time to die.
وهناك وقت للموت
I've stood at the deathbed
لقد وقفت على فراش موت
of several famous people,
العديد من المشاهير
whom you would know.
الذين ربما تعرفونهم
I've talked to them.
تحدثت إليهم.
I've seen them in those agonizing moments
رأيتهم في تلك اللحظات المؤلمة
when they were scared to death.
عندما كانوا خائفين حتى الموت
And yet, a few years earlier,
وبعد ذلك بسنوات قليلة
death never crossed their mind.
لم يكن الموت أبدا في حساباتهم
I talked to a woman this past week
لقد تحدثت الى امرأة في الاسبوع الماضي
whose father
والدها..
was a famous doctor.
والدها.. طبيب شهير
She said he never thought of God, never talked about God,
وقالت إنه لم يكن يفكر في الله أو يتحدث عنه قط
didn't believe in God. He was an atheist.
لم يكن ليؤمن بالله، كان ملحدا
But she said,
لكنها قالت
as he came to die,
عندما جاءه الموت
he sat up on the side of the bed one day,
جلس على حافة فراشه ذلك اليوم
and he asked the nurse if he could see the chaplain.
وطلب من الممرضة أن يرى قسيس.
And he said, for the first time in his life
وقال لأول مرة في حياته
he'd thought about the inevitable,
أنه كان قد فكر في الموت
and about God.
وفي الله
Was there a God?
هل كان الله موجوداً؟
A few years ago, a university student asked me,
وقبل بضع سنوات ، سألني طالب جامعي
"What is the greatest surprise in your life?"
ما هي أكبر مفاجأة في حياتك؟
And I said, "The greatest surprise in my life
وقلت ، أكبر مفاجأة في حياتي
is the brevity of life.
هي قصر الحياة
It passes so fast."
إنها تمر بسرعة!
But it does not need to have to be that way.
إلا أنه لا حاجة إلى أن تكون الأمور على هذا النحو
Wernher von Braun,
ويرنر فون براون ،
in the aftermath of World War II concluded, quote:
في أعقاب الحرب العالمية الثانية، يقول
"science and religion are not antagonists.
العلم والدين ليسا متضادين
On the contrary, they're sisters."
على العكس من ذلك ، إنهما في وفاق!
He put it on a personal basis.
لقد قال ذلك كرأيه الخاص
I knew Dr. von Braun very well.
كنت أعرف الدكتور فون براون جيدا
And he said, "Speaking for myself,
وكان يقول : عندما أتحدث عن نفسي
I can only say that the grandeur of the cosmos
لا يسعني إلا أن أقول أن عظمة الكون
serves only to confirm
فقط لتؤكد
a belief in the certainty of a creator."
الاعتقاد بوجود خالق له
He also said,
وقال ايضا
"In our search to know God,
في سعينا لمعرفة الله ،
I've come to believe that the life of Jesus Christ
توصلت للإيمان بأن حياة المسيح
should be the focus of our efforts and inspiration.
يجب أن تكون محل اهتمامنا
The reality of this life and His resurrection
وأن حقيقة حياته وبعثه
is the hope of mankind."
هي أمل البشرية
I've done a lot of speaking in Germany
لقد تحدثت كثيرا في ألمانيا
and in France, and in different parts of the world --
وفي فرنسا ، وفي أنحاء مختلفة من العالم
105 countries it's been my privilege to speak in.
وكان لي شرف التحدث في 105 دولة
And I was invited one day to visit
وكنت قد دعيت ذات يوم لزيارة
Chancellor Adenauer,
المستشار أديناور
who was looked upon as sort of the founder of modern Germany,
والذي يعتبر من مؤسسي ألمانيا الحديثة
since the war.
منذ الحرب
And he once -- and he said to me,
قال لي في إحدى المرات
he said, "Young man." He said,
قال: أيها الشاب..
"Do you believe in the resurrection of Jesus Christ?"
هل تؤمن ببعث المسيح؟
And I said, "Sir, I do."
فأجبته: نعم، سيدي
He said, "So do I."
فقال: وأنا كذلك
He said, "When I leave office,
عندما أترك منصبي
I'm going to spend my time writing a book
سوف أقضي وقتي في تأليف كتاب
on why Jesus Christ rose again,
عن الأسباب وراء بعث اليسوع مرة أخرى
and why it's so important to believe that."
وأهمية الإيمان بذلك
In one of his plays,
في إحدى مسرحياته
Alexander Solzhenitsyn
يصور لنا الكسندر سولجنستين
depicts a man dying,
رجلا يحتضر
who says to those gathered around his bed,
قائلا لهؤلاء الذين التفوا حول فراشه
"The moment when it's terrible to feel regret
إن أصعب اللحظات التي تشعر فيها بالندم
is when one is dying."
هي عندما يحتضر أحدهم
How should one live in order not to feel regret when one is dying?
كيف ينبغي لشخص أن يعيش حتى لا يشعر بالندم عندما يأتيه الموت؟
Blaise Pascal
بليز باسكال
asked exactly that question
سأل هذا السؤال على وجه الدقة
in seventeenth-century France.
في القرن السابع عشر في فرنسا
Pascal has been called the architect
باسكال كان يطلق عليه لقب مهندس الحضارة الحديثة
of modern civilization.
مهندس الحضارة الحديثة
He was a brilliant scientist
لقد كان عالما براقا
at the frontiers of mathematics,
في علم الرياضيات
even as a teenager.
حتى عندما كان مراهقا
He is viewed by many as the founder of the probability theory,
ويعتبره الكثيرون مؤسس نظرية الاحتمالات
and a creator of the first model of a computer.
ومبدع أول نموذج للكمبيوتر
And of course, you are all familiar with
وطبعا كلكم على علم
the computer language named for him.
أن هناك لغة برمجة تحمل اسمه
Pascal explored in depth our human dilemmas
أبحر باسكال بعمق في معضلاتنا البشرية
of evil, suffering and death.
من شر ومعاناة وموت
He was astounded
وكان مذهولا
at the phenomenon we've been considering:
من الظاهرة التي كنا نتبناها
that people can achieve extraordinary heights
يمكن للناس تحقيق مستويات عالية غير مألوفة
in science, the arts and human enterprise,
في مجالات العلوم والفنون ، والمؤسسات البشرية
yet they also are full of anger, hypocrisy
ولكنها أيضا مليئة بالغضب ، والنفاق
and have -- and self-hatreds.
والأحقاد
Pascal saw us as a remarkable mixture
قدم لنا باسكال مزيجا رائعا
of genius and self-delusion.
من العبقرية وخداع الذات
On November 23,
ففي الثالث والعشرين من نوفمبر
1654,
سنة 1654
Pascal had a profound religious experience.
تعرض باسكال لتجربة دينية عميقة
He wrote in his journal these words:
وكتب تلك الكلمات في إحدى المجلات
"I submit myself,
أقدم نفسي
absolutely,
كلية
to Jesus Christ, my redeemer."
ليسوع المسيح.. مخلصي
A French historian said,
وقال مؤرخ فرنسي
two centuries later,
بعد ذلك بقرنين
"Seldom has so mighty an intellect
نادرا ما يقدم الأقوياء والأذكياء
submitted with such humility
هذا التواضع
to the authority of Jesus Christ."
لسلطة يسوع المسيح
Pascal came to believe not only the love and the grace of God
لم يقتصر إيمان باسكال على قدرة حب الله ورحمته
could bring us back into harmony,
على أن تعيد الوئام بيننا
but he believed
لكنه آمن أيضا
that his own sins and failures could be forgiven,
أن ذنوبه وخطاياه يمكن أن تغفر
and that when he died he would go to a place called heaven.
وأنه عندما يموت سيذهب إلى مكان يدعى الجنة
He experienced it in a way that went beyond
لقد تعرض إلى تلك الخبرة بطريقة تجاوزت
scientific observation and reason.
حدود الملاحظة العلمية والتعقل
It was he who penned the well-known words,
إنه من خط تلك الكلمات المشهورة
"The heart has its reasons,
القلب له أسبابه
which reason knows not of."
والتي لا يعرف سببا لها.
Equally well known is Pascal's Wager.
كما عرف عنه أيضا رهانه المشهور
Essentially, he said this: "if you bet on God,
كان يقول: إذا راهنت على الله
and open yourself to his love,
وتفتحت نفسك على حبه
you lose nothing, even if you're wrong.
فلن تخسر شيئا ولو كنت على خطأ
But if instead you bet that there is no God,
ولكنك إذا راهنت على عدم وجوده
then you can lose it all, in this life and the life to come."
فإنك قد تخسر تلك الحياة.. وما قد يليها
For Pascal, scientific knowledge
كانت المعرفة العلمية لدى باسكال
paled beside the knowledge of God.
باهتة بجانب معرفة الله
The knowledge of God was far beyond
لقد كانت معرفة الله أبعد
anything that ever crossed his mind.
عن أي شيء خطر على ذهنه
He was ready to face him
لقد كان مستعدا لمواجهته
when he died at the age of 39.
عندما توفي عن عمر يناهز 39
King David lived to be 70,
عاش الملك داوود حتى السبعين من عمره
a long time in his era.
منذ وقت طويل في عصره
Yet he too had to face death,
إلا أنه واجه الموت أيضا في النهاية
and he wrote these words:
وسطر هذه الكلمات
"even though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death,
على الرغم من مضيي خلال وادي ظلال الموت
I will fear no evil,
لن أخاف شرا
for you are with me."
لأنك (الله) معي
This was David's answer to three dilemmas
كان هذا رد داوود على المعضلات الثلاث
of evil, suffering and death.
الشر والمعاناة والموت.
It can be yours, as well,
وأنت أيضا يمكنك امتلاك هذه الإجابة
as you seek the living God
إذا سعيت إلى الله
and allow him to fill your life
وملأت به حياتك
and give you hope for the future.
وجعلته أملك في المستقبل
When I was 17 years of age,
عندما كنت في السابعة عشر من العمر
I was born and reared on a farm in North Carolina.
نشأت في مزرعة بولاية كارولينا الشمالية
I milked cows every morning, and I had to milk the same cows every evening
أحلب الأبقار كل صباح، وأحلبها ثانية في المساء
when I came home from school.
عندما جئت إلى البيت عائدا من المدرسة
And there were 20 of them that I had --
كانت هناك عشرين بقرة
that I was responsible for,
كنت مسؤولا عنهم
and I worked on the farm
وعملت في المزرعة
and tried to keep up with my studies.
وحاولت الانتظام في دراستي
I didn't make good grades in high school.
لم أحقق درجات جيدة في المدرسة الثانوية
I didn't make them in college, until
ولم أحققها حتى في الكلية.. حتى
something happened in my heart.
حدث شيء ما في قلبي.
One day, I was faced face-to-face
يوم ما ، كنت وجها لوجه
with Christ.
مع المسيح
He said, "I am the way, the truth and the life."
وقال : أنا الطريق، والحق، والحياة
Can you imagine that? "I am the truth.
هل يمكن لك ان تتخيل ذلك؟ قال: أنا الحقيقة
I'm the embodiment of all truth."
أنا تجسيد كل حقيقة
He was a liar.
ربما كان كاذبا
Or he was insane.
أو مجنونا
Or he was what he claimed to be.
أو كان ما ادعى أنه هو
Which was he?
ماذا كان؟
I had to make that decision.
كان علي اتخاذ هذا القرار
I couldn't prove it.
لا أستطيع إثبات ذلك
I couldn't take it to a laboratory
لم أستطع إحضارها إلى مختبر
and experiment with it.
وإخضاعها للتجارب
But by faith I said, I believe him,
ولكني قلت بإيمان، أنا أصدقه
and he came into my heart
ولقد سكن إلى قلبي
and changed my life.
وغير حياتي
And now I'm ready,
والآن.. أنا مستعد
when I hear that call,
عندما أسمع هذا النداء
to go into the presence of God.
للدخول في معية الله
Thank you, and God bless all of you.
شكرا لكم ، وبارك الله لكم جميعا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you for the privilege. It was great.
أشكركم على هذا الشرف، لقد كان عظيما
Richard Wurman: You did it.
ريتشارد فورمان: لقد فعلتها!
Thanks.
شكرا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)